in this video we're going to go through
all the ido calculus around the
stochastic dynamics of actually creating
a modified eunstein ulembek process for
modelling temperature data this is for
the final use of actually using this
model to price temperature and exotic
options so without further ado if you're
interested in weather derivatives and
you would like to learn more about ido
calculus in general let's dive into it
so the first part of this is going to be
the math and then we're going to
actually use python and fit some of
these coefficients so first off the
cyclic nature of temperature time series
justifies the use of a mean reverting
process in its modelling of its dynamic
so many people have actually modeled
this as an ito process as a continuous
stochastic process with a mean reversion
property and that can be the ornstein
ulbec process so these following papers
have looked at how you can implement
this
now why would you not implement a normal
mean reverting onside ulembek process
so here is our general ou process and
here we've got our change in temperature
dynamics equal to a mean reversion
parameter k with our long term
average temperature and that is
constantly changing minus the
temperature that we're currently at now
and that's all our drift component plus
some volatility component that is time
dependent so this is a normal mean
reverting ornstein ulembek process maybe
bar the dynamics here of our change in
temperature and then our change in
average temperature and then our change
in volatility the first point to note is
that to actually capture the full mean
reverting dynamics of the temperature
it's so important to have an expectation
of the temperature that's equal to the
average temperature so now we're going
to explain that while using the normal
mean reverting ornstein ulembek process
and if this was constant volatility over
time you might call this the versailles
model for interest rates
but essentially we're going to go
through why this is not the best choice
for temperature so to prove this we're
going to use it o calculus and more
specifically we're going to use the ito
doblin formula now the eaton doblin
formula here is written in differential
form and this is where we have
our dynamics of a given function f where
x is an ito process and that can be
explained as the partial derivative of
this function with respect to t dt plus
the partial different derivative with
respect to x so our edo process dx plus
a half
and then the second partial differential
with respect to x um dx dx so this is
the eden double and formula if you want
to look for proofs i can do a video on
that but um i'm guessing not a lot of
people are interested in pure ito
calculus and more interested in the
application so without further ado let's
get into the application the hard part
here and for our model in general is
going to be about choosing this function
so we're going to follow a similar
methodology as solving the cox ingersoll
and ross interest rate model so the cir
model so we're going to choose an
exponential function with our mean
reverting parameter
with respect to time times by our edo
process now this choice may seem random
but really it's not the main reason
we're choosing this is because when we
solve a normal or rhyming integral
non-stochastic integral
by the integra integrating factor method
we end up with a choice that's best
suited as the exponential of the
integral of whatever's in front of our
y process dynamics now that's
therefore our integrating factor method
being applied here multiplied by our ito
process so it is a logical choice our
partial derivative with respect to t
ends up with this function here partial
derivative with respect to x and then
our second order partial differential
gets zero so now that we've actually
found out these functions we can plug
them into the ido doblin formula and
then we're going to start subbing in our
edo process
so our sde specifically so now we're
going to apply this itodoblin formula
with that function that we've just
specified
to our ido process on temperature with
our dynamics of dt temperature as
described by our mean reverting sde that
we had before
so now i've just plotted out
the actual dynamics of our function e to
the kt
multiplied by t is going to be equal to
the itodoblin formula and now you'll
notice that here instead of x for the
ito process i've placed the temperature
t and the dynamics t
with respect to that x variable so once
we substitute in what those
functional partial derivatives were we
end up with a 0 in this second order
term here so that cancels and then we're
left with the following drift term
and then
e our integrating factor
multiplied by our original dt dynamics
as described by that sde so if we then
substitute in the dt dynamics what we
get is our drift term of the sde
so we've subbed it in the dt dynamics
there
we get our drift term multiplied by that
integrating factor plus the integrating
factor multiplied by the diffusion terms
we can now cross
cross out cancelling terms so here we
identify that this part of the drift
term of temperature
can actually be crossed out with this
drift term that we had from our ido
doblin formula so we can cross that out
and essentially we get left with one
single drift term
with respect to that average temperature
plus our diffusion term multiplied by
that
integrating factor there so now what
we're going to do is take the integral
over a given unit of time our interval
is going to be from s to t where t is
greater than s absolutely
so
here we get on the left hand side we're
going to take the integral of
this dynamics of this equation and what
you get is
our two components here over those two
different times so we've got e to the
power of kt
times t t and then we've got minus e to
the k
uh kappa s
t s equals our integrals over our
deterministic uh or our drift and then
our diffusion based
terms so once we take the integral
essentially we're going to take
our
terms
with s so
with time smaller to the right hand side
and then we're going to change the base
of the ryman integral to d hat t
now we also going to divide through by
our coefficient there on the left hand
side our integrating factor and note
there that it is a t
so now we have the solution to our
temperature
sde however we can actually simplify
this a little bit further so we can
actually take this integral over this
domain
and then we can group like terms so we
end up with our final temperature
solution being this and what we'll
actually know the big issue is that the
expectation is not the long run average
temperature so how do we determine here
this this is our final solution for
temperature under a normal mean
reverting ou dynamics but when we have
the ito integral the expectation of a
needle integral is equal to zero
so we arrive at the expectation equal to
this stuff here and we can see clearly
that that is not
t hat which is our average in our daily
average temperature series
so this happens because the mean process
of the equation is reverting to hat t
but this is not constant over time this
changes from one time step to another
so remember in the last video if you
haven't watched it i'll link it up in
the description above then we have a
observed auto correlation in the error
terms so here's our fitted model of that
temperature hat
and essentially what we have is our
model in terms of a linear component and
then a seasonal component the seasonal
component was captured with just a sine
function
now we observed in the residuals here
are the residuals here but we've noticed
partial autocorrelation with one lag and
essentially this is no coincidence
because as it happens when we add this
ar1 term for changes in the seasonally
adjusted mean so this d hat t this
change in the uh seasonally adjusted
mean this is going to adjust the drift
um in the long run to the actual mean of
hat t essentially our solution can be
solved by adding this seizure the change
in the seasonally adjusted means
to
our actual sde dynamics so original work
first published by donor and quaral
sorry if i butchered those names but
essentially by adding this new dynamics
to our drift term we can account
for this change and that this solution
of the dynamics leads to an expectation
of temperature which is equal to
our
average temperature as we've defined in
the seasonal mean so essentially we
could use the ido doblin formula again
but it turns out that we can actually
solve this sde using a traditional
integrating factor method
and multiplying through by this
integrating factor note that we cannot
handle this for the stochastic component
but we're just going to consider the
drift term for a second here so all we
do is we're going to multiply through
that integrating factor into our sde as
we have there and we're going to
separate out the parts what we'll notice
is that this combination here is
actually the product of the differential
and what i mean by that it is the
dynamics of
the integrating factor multiplied by our
temperature hat minus temperature at
that time and that's equal to our
variance our diffusion component
so to prove that the expectation is
equal to zero if we consider this new
ito process then in terms of this
dynamics here of our
our product between our integrating
factor and this term here
then the dynamics are as the equation
above essentially we can just call the
dynamics of zt which is equal to the
dynamics of the formula that we have
here so if we change that to an ito
integral form we end up with the
following dynamic zt equals z0
minus our diffusion component
now if we substitute in what our zt
definition was and then we
use the fact that attempt at our initial
conditions at temperature zero equals
the average temperature zero well then
we end up with the following
substituting in for both time periods at
time zero and time t we end up with that
so now if we rearrange so this cancels
and this component cancels out here
because the initial conditions are that
they're equal and then we can take this
component this exponential divide
through to the other side and then
subtract our
hat to temperature hat our average and
essentially by rearranging you end up
with a following solution here where our
temperature
is equal to our average temperature plus
a variance process and of course the
expectation of this edo process is then
equal to uh the average temperature and
the the reason is again because this ido
integral the expectation in syria so now
we're going to consider the modified
ornstein erlenbeck process so the
dynamics as we've just described we're
very convinced that the expectation of
this new stochastic process is equal to
the long run average of this daily
average temperature time series so
here's our model
and here we're going to
describe our changing average of this
daily average temperature so our hat
t
is actually equal to a equation that we
worked out in our previous video so this
is how we modeled our time series in
terms of a trend and then our seasonal
components with our estimated parameters
so one of the parameters that we haven't
um actually estimated yet within our
ornstein illinois process is our
speed of mean reversion so our kappa
here in the chart we can see that now if
i take away that
that deterministic seasonal mean
component that
hat t away from our
daily average temperature series we end
up with these residuals and essentially
i need to fit a process to this now one
clue that we can see here is that again
as we noted in our previous video
that the partial autocorrelation
function shows that there is a
correlation with the first order lag so
that should be a hint but we'll do the
euler discretization of our sde over the
intervals between i minus 1 and i
so by completing the euler
discretization we get temperature i
minus
ti minus 1 equals the average
temperature i minus average temperature
i minus 1 plus our kappa
and multiplied by this term here of our
previous average temperature minus our
temperature that we observed beforehand
plus
a
volatility
based on our current position multiplied
by z i n here that is just normally
distributed um with standard deviation
equal to 1.
if i now rearrange this equation so i
take each of the individual time series
and with respect to the time period that
i'm in currently
i subtract away our average daily
temperature
then that should remind you of our
de-trended and remove seasonality
time series that we had modeled
previously that we observed the one lag
in and essentially what we're going to
denote that is is just our
t
hat component it's getting so it's
confusing with the notation but
essentially our time series where we had
the residuals before
with our time series that has just been
detrended and then seasonality removed
is now going to be called
t
hat and instead of it being a bar it is
now a hat so if we simplify it enough
then we can actually model this as an
autoregressive model
with one lag term
so essentially here our
our kappa is equal to one minus gamma
where our gamma is going to be the
coefficient that we fit
this ar model process to so now
estimating that speed of mean reversion
all we need to do is fit this
autoregressive model with one lag series
here we're going to use the stats models
module from python to do this and
essentially we end up with a coefficient
of 0.56
for our gamma and therefore our kappa is
0.438 or thereabouts so now our modified
um ornstein ulenbek dynamics with
estimated parameters in total we have
the daily average temperature dynamics
we've defined that in the equation
we have the change in average daily
average temperature for that's a
mouthful so our
bar t our hat t
which is equal to our trend component
and then our seasonal component
we also have
a complete equation for the first
derivative of that average daily average
temperature
which is
this component here
because we can just derive this with
respect to time and essentially we just
end up
with one less term which drops out and
our sign turns to a cos function my
question to you is what's missing and
what haven't we actually done yet well
essentially it's this term here it's our
sigma it's our volatility that we
haven't considered now the dynamics of
temperature volatility as you can see
even just in this graph our variance is
not the same between periods i can see
here
that towards the ends of the years or
the starts of the years we have massive
volatility or changes in temperatures in
our residuals and the reason that is
occurring is because that's summer so
potentially um volatility is not
constant throughout
the different seasons so if we actually
look at each individual day over those
160 years and we measure the volatility
standard deviation as a
way of looking at the volatility or
volatility as we have in the orange
there where the volatility is just the
percentage of that standard deviation
with respect
to our mean well then you get something
that looks like this and you can see
that depending on the time of year
volatility does in fact change now we
could model this in a number of ways
we're going to look at how to model it
so in the next video we're going to
learn how to model it with fourier
series parametric regression so
potentially a polynomial we'll look at
local and non-parametric regression so
splines and then how we can actually
estimate this potentially looking at
just months with piecewise non-constant
functions so potentially individual
seasons or individual months the last
the last way to model it is actually by
coming up with another ornstein
mean reverting process but for this time
it's going to be volatility so then we
would have two stochastic differential
equations once we've actually defined
what that volatility model is in any one
of these ways then you can go ahead and
then using your risk neutral pricing
framework of these dynamics so with
respect to a market price of risk you
can then go ahead and price uh
temperature options uh using these
dynamics that we've defined if you
enjoyed the video give it a thumbs up
and look for the next video if you're
interested in following on with this
series
[Music]
you